<mets:METS xmlns:mets="http://www.loc.gov/METS/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:dim="http://www.dspace.org/xmlns/dspace/dim" PROFILE="DSPACE METS SIP Profile 1.0" LABEL="DSpace Collection" OBJID="/handle/2027.42/114391" ID="hdl:2027.42/114391">
<mets:dmdSec GROUPID="group_dmd_0" ID="dmd_1">
<mets:mdWrap OTHERMDTYPE="DIM" MDTYPE="OTHER">
<mets:xmlData>
<dim:dim dspaceType="COLLECTION">
<dim:field mdschema="dc" element="description">
<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<form style="display:inline" action="http://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/handle/2027.42/114391/browse?">
<input type="submit" value="View all items in this collection"/>
</form>
</p>
<br xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>


<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<img src="http://deepblue.lib.umich.edu/static/image/bentley-banner.jpg" alt="Bentley Historical Library banner"/>
</p>

<h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prison Creative Arts Project collection</h2>

<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The materials in this online repository form part of a larger Prison Creative Arts Project collection held by the <a href="http://bentley.umich.edu/">Bentley Historical Library</a>.  For a more complete index to the materials, please consult the collection's <a href="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/b/bhlead/umich-bhl-2010177">online finding aid</a>.
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
For questions or more information, please contact the Bentley Historical Library's <a href="mailto:bentley.ref@umich.edu">Division of Reference and Access Services</a>
</p>

<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<b>Abstract:</b>
<br/>
Nonprofit established in 1990 to provide and facilitate creative arts experiences for Michigan prisoners.  Materials in this online repository include a theatrical production.
</p>

<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<b>History:</b>
<br/>
Prison Creative Arts Project was established in 1990 by University of Michigan professor Buzz Alexander to work with incarcerated Michigan adults and youths in the creative arts, including theater, creative writing, art, dance and music.
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
The Prison Creative Arts Project (PCAP) was founded in 1990 with the mission to collaborate with incarcerated adults, incarcerated youth, urban youth and the formerly incarcerated to strengthen our community through creative expression. Housed in the University of Michigan&#8217;s Residential College, faculty and students work with community members both inside and outside prisons to engage in workshops in theatre, dance, visual art, creative writing, slam poetry, and music. Annually, PCAP hosts one of the largest prisoner art exhibitions in the world and publishes a literary journal of writing by incarcerated authors. With arts programming and events year round, the organization serves as a creative hub for those with links to the criminal justice system, community volunteers, faculty, students, and university staff. (From <a href="http://www.lsa.umich.edu/pcap/">Prison Creative Arts Project website</a>.)
</p>
</dim:field>
<dim:field qualifier="abstract" mdschema="dc" element="description"/>
<dim:field qualifier="tableofcontents" mdschema="dc" element="description"/>
<dim:field qualifier="uri" mdschema="dc" element="identifier">http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/114391</dim:field>
<dim:field mdschema="dc" element="provenance"/>
<dim:field mdschema="dc" element="rights">
<h2 xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Please note:</h2>
<p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Copyright has been transferred to the Regents of the University of Michigan.</p>
<br xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"/>
</dim:field>
<dim:field qualifier="license" mdschema="dc" element="rights">As the designated coordinator for this Deep Blue Collection, I am authorized by the Community members to serve as their representative in all dealings with the Repository. As the designee, I ensure that I have read the Deep Blue policies. Furthermore, I have conveyed to the community the terms and conditions outlined in those policies, including the language of the standard deposit license quoted below and that the community members have granted me the authority to deposit content on their behalf.</dim:field>
<dim:field mdschema="dc" element="title">Prison Creative Arts Project collection</dim:field>
</dim:dim>
</mets:xmlData>
</mets:mdWrap>
</mets:dmdSec>
<mets:structMap LABEL="DSpace" TYPE="LOGICAL">
<mets:div DMDID="dmd_1" TYPE="DSpace Collection"/>
</mets:structMap>
</mets:METS>