<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<record xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/MARC21/slim" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/MARC21/slim http://www.loc.gov/standards/marcxml/schema/MARC21slim.xsd">
  <leader>00000npca 2200757za 4500</leader>
  <controlfield tag="005">20070626084817.0</controlfield>
  <controlfield tag="008">951103i18991994miu||          | |||eng d</controlfield>
  <datafield tag="035" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">(OCoLC)ocm78545582</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="035" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">(OCoLC)ocm78545582</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="040" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">MiU-H</subfield>
    <subfield code="c">MiU-H</subfield>
    <subfield code="e">appm</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="100" ind1="1" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Cisler, Walker, L.</subfield>
    <subfield code="q">(Walker Lee),</subfield>
    <subfield code="d">1897-1994.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="245" ind1="0" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Walker L. Cisler papers,</subfield>
    <subfield code="f">1899-1994</subfield>
    <subfield code="g">(bulk 1943-1987)</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="300" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">33 linear ft. and 1 oversize volume.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Detroit Edison executive, advocate of the need to develop peaceful uses for nuclear power.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Walker Lee Cisler was born in Marietta, Ohio, in 1896. After graduating from Cornell in 1922 with a degree in mechanical engineering, he accepted a cadet position with the Public Service Electric and Gas Company of New Jersey. During this two year appointment, on-the-job training was augmented by participation in company study groups and evening courses in business and economics at New York University.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Over the next two decades, Cisler rose through the ranks and eventually became Assistant General Manager of Power Plants.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">In 1941 Cisler was appointed to the Office of Production Management (OPM), a division of the War Production Board (WPB). The OPM was composed of three industry consultants working in conjunction with federal planners to coordinate production for civilian and military consumption. As a member of the Power Division, Walker Cisler was responsible for balancing allied demands for electricity against domestic power requirements.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">While engaged in this war service, Cisler accepted a position as Chief Engineer of Power Plants with the Detroit Edison Company. Effective October 1, 1943, this appointment was not actualized immediately as Cisler was first commissioned as a Lieutenant Colonel in the United States Army and sent to the Mediterranean theatre to survey electrical facilities. This three-month term of service was repeatedly extended and a promotion to full Colonel followed.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">In 1944, on the recommendation of the Secretary of the Army, Walker Cisler was appointed to General Eisenhower's staff as Chief of the Public Utilities Section, Supreme Headquarters, Allied Expeditionary Forces (SHAEF). In this position, he assumed primary responsibility for the restoration of electrical services in recently liberated areas.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">With the cessation of hostilities in Europe, Cisler served in Berlin as Chief of the Public Utilities Section in the Office of Military Government in Germany. Even with the termination of his active duty status in late 1945, Cisler continued his involvement in European reconstruction as principal advisor to the State Department on electrical power issues.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">He also worked as chief consultant on electrical power to the Economic Corporation Administration (ECA) and successor organizations, the Mutual Security Agency (MSA), the Foreign Operations Administration (FOA), and the International Cooperation Administration (ICA). Cisler was officially discharged from military service in 1952.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Upon his return from Europe in 1945, Cisler assumed the duties of Chief Engineer of Power Plants with the Detroit Edison Company. By 1947 he had also been appointed Vice President of Employee Relations. In 1948, his expanded duties were consolidated under the title executive vice presidnet. In 1951, he was appointed to the Board of Directors and subsequently promoted to President and General Manager.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Upon the retirement of Prentiss M. Brown in 1954, Walker Cisler was confirmed as Chief Executive Officer of Detroit Edison. He served in this capacity until 1971 at which time he was succeeded by William G. Meese. In 1964 Walker Cisler was elected Chairman of the Board of Directors, a post he held until 1975.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">While at Detroit Edison, Walker Cisler focused a great deal of attention on the development of atomic power as a commercial resource. To this end he served as Executive Secretary to the Industrial Advisory Board of the Atomic Energy Commission (AEC) beginning in 1947. Under his direction, the board issued a report to the AEC in 1951 requesting permission to begin industrial development of a fast neutron breeder reactor.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">This report led directly to a feasibility study conducted by the newly formed Nuclear Power Development Department of the AEC. By 1953, twenty-six power utilities and large corporations nationwide had expressed interest in collaborating on the project. And in 1954, Congress amended the Atomic Energy Act and thus empowered the AEC to license the distribution of fuel for commercial nuclear development and to exercise oversight of construction and safety standards.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Having cleared all legal obstacles to the construction of a commercially managed nuclear reactor, a consortium of electric power systems, engineering, and manufacturing firms established in 1954 the Atomic Power Development Corporation (APDA). Recognized as a leader in the field, Walker Cisler agreed to serve as President and to work to cordinate collaboration in the research and development of a fast neutron breeder reactor.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Power Reactor Development Associates (PRDC), a companion corporation to APDA was established to handle actual construction and operation of the first commercially managed nuclear reactor. With Walker Cisler as President in 1956, PRDC functioned as a legal buffer in limiting the liability of APDA's member organizations.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Under Cisler's guidance, APDA and PRDC jointly constituted a vehicle for national participation in the development of the Enrico Fermi Nuclear Power Plant at Lagoona Beach, Monroe County, Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">As a member of both APDA and PRDC and through the involvement of its managerial and technical personnel, Detroit Edison participated in the construction and operation of Fermi. Detroit Edison also owned and operated the steam generators and steam turbine facilities needed to convert heat generated by the reactor into electrical power suitable for distribution.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Over the next seventeen years, from 1955 to 1972, Cisler and the Fermi plant were closely associated in the public's mind. Despite the ultimate failure of the plant (the reactor was decommissioned in 1972), Cisler never wavered in his espousal of the need to develop peaceful uses for nuclear power. He also saw the need to involve the international community in this effort.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">He was among the founders of the World Power Conference (WPC) and its successor organization, the World Energy Conference (WEC). In 1968, Cisler was elected chairman of the International Executive Council of WEC, and in 1974, under his leadership, Detroit hosted the meeting of the full body of the WEC.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Cisler retired from Detroit Edison in 1975, but remained active in the international energy scene primarily through his work with Overseas Advisory Associates Inc. (OAAI), which he had founded in 1972 to utilize the expertise of retired energy executives for overseas consulting. OAAI functioned globally, but focused on activity in the Middle and Far East. The most intensive OAAI contracts involved the establishment of a modern energy infrastructure in Saudi Arabia.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">In addition, Cisler was active in scientific, civic, political, and business affairs throughout his career. He served as the long-time Chairman of the Thomas Alva Edison Foundation. He also served on the boards of directors of a wide range of organizations devoted to revitalizing Detroit and improving the public welfare. He presided over many programs sponsored by the Economic Club of Detroit and served as a member and interim Chairman of Fruehauf Corporation's Board of Directors.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Walker Cisler remained active in his many endeavors until his death on October 18, 1994, at the age of 97.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The papers of Walker L. Cisler are divided into nine series: Atomic Power Development Associates (APDA), Detroit Edison, War Service, Personal File, Speeches, Overseas Advisory Associates (OAAI), Other Affiliations, Visual Materials, and Sound Recordings.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The Atomic Power Development Associates' (APDA) series (13 linear ft.; 1950-1977), is composed of two sub-series: President's File, and APDA Technology Reports. The APDA President's File contains records of WLC's APDA and Power Reactor Development Associates (PRDC) activities.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">These files relate principally to the development, construction, administration, and operation of the Enrico Fermi Nuclear Power Plant and auxiliary facilities. The APDA Technology Reports (267 volumes with index) detail the results of research conducted in conjunction with the large fast breeder reactor development program.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The Detroit Edison series (1 linear ft.; 1945-1989) details Walker Cisler's long involvement with the Detroit Edison Company. This series includes annual reports, board materials originally serving a decision support function, correspondence, and topical files relating to the administration of Detroit Edison. Also included are official publications, newspaper clippings, and magazine articles pertaining to Walker Cisler.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The War Service series (1 linear ft.; 1918-1919 and 1943-1953) documents Walker Cisler's service record and includes, in addition to official document, war-related correspondence and notebooks. This series includes detailed information on power issues in various European nations during the war. Other files document his affiliation with the War Production Board, the Office of the Military Government of Germany, and the Public Utilities Committee (SHAEF).</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The Personal File series (2 linear ft.; 1933-1994), includes genealogical and biographical information, correspondence, publications, and files detailing his many international commitments and activities.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The Speeches series (8 linear ft.; 1933-1987) includes copies of both published and unpublished speeches.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The Overseas Advisory Associates (OAAI) series (4 linear ft.; 1974-1993), is composed primarily of geographically organized telexes relating to consulting activities of OAAI. A substantial portion of the file relates to activities in Saudi Arabia.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The Other Affiliations series (2 linear ft.; 1918-1989) contains records of Walker Cisler's affiliation with the Economic Club of Detroit, New Detroit, the Fruehauf Corporation, and other civic and fraternal organizations.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Visual Materials (1.5 linear ft. and 1 oversize volume; 1899-1985) includes photographs and photograph ablums. The photographs include portraits, group photographs, and photographs arranged by topic. All group photographs include Walker Cisler. The albums consist of commemorative volumes prepared on the occasion of special events, such as WLC's retirement as chairman of the board of Detroit Edison.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Sound Recordings (5 reels; 1958 and 1973) consists of a speech of WLC at the dedication of the Mackinac Bridge in 1958, and a series of four lectures given at Albion College in 1973 on the topic of energy.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="555" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Finding aid in the library.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="555" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Finding aid available via World Wide Web at URL: http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead&amp;idno=umich-bhl-9573</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="500" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Donor: 8314</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="500" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Visual materials described separately.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="600" ind1="1" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Cisler, Walker, L.</subfield>
    <subfield code="q">(Walker Lee),</subfield>
    <subfield code="d">1897-1994.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Atomic Power Development Associates, inc.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Detroit Edison Company.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Fruehauf Corporation.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Economic Club of Detroit.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">New Detroit, Inc. (Detroit, Mich.)</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Electric power</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Nuclear power plants</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Enrico Fermi Nuclear Power Plant (Mich.)</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Overseas Advisory Associates, Inc.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">World Power Conference.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">World War, 1939-1945.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Power Reactor Development Company.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="852" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Bentley Historical Library,</subfield>
    <subfield code="a">University of Michigan,</subfield>
    <subfield code="e">Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109-2113</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="856" ind1="4" ind2="2">
    <subfield code="3">Finding aid:</subfield>
    <subfield code="u">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead&amp;idno=umich-bhl-9573</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="998" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">TEP</subfield>
  </datafield>
</record>
