<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<record xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/MARC21/slim" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/MARC21/slim http://www.loc.gov/standards/marcxml/schema/MARC21slim.xsd">
  <leader>00000npca 2200625za 4500</leader>
  <controlfield tag="005">20140327132215.0</controlfield>
  <controlfield tag="008">970508i19632009miu                 eng d</controlfield>
  <datafield tag="035" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">(OCoLC)ocm82113542</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="040" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">MiU-H</subfield>
    <subfield code="c">MiU-H</subfield>
    <subfield code="e">appm</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="100" ind1="1" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Toy, James W.,</subfield>
    <subfield code="d">1930-</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="245" ind1="1" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">James W. Toy papers,</subfield>
    <subfield code="f">1963-2009</subfield>
    <subfield code="g">(bulk 1971-1994).</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="300" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">27.5 linear feet (in 30 boxes) and 1 oversize folder.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">James Toy, an activist on behalf of gay-lesbian rights, was founder and co-head of the Human Sexuality Office of the University of Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">In 1970, James Toy helped to found and served as secretary of both the Detroit Gay Liberation Movement and the Ann Arbor Gay Liberation Front, organizations established to dramatize and seek remedy for the discrimination and harassment that gays and lesbians daily confronted. In April of 1970 Toy made his first public pronouncement as an "open" gay male at an anti-war rally in Detroit.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Also in 1970, Toy and other students proposed that the University of Michigan should create a unit to address the needs of gay and lesbian students. In 1971, the university under its Office of Special Services and Programs created a Human Sexuality Office. James Toy served as Gay Male Advocate (later co-coordinator) of this unit until 1994.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Toy was also a dedicated member of St. Joseph's Episcopal Church in Detroit and a concerned and valuable worker within the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan. Beginning in 1971, he served as a member of the diocesan commission on homosexuality; in 1975, he helped establish a Detroit area chapter of Integrity, a gay Episcopal organization; in 1976, he became a member of the diocesan Church and Society Committee;</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">and since 1989, he has been a member of the diocese's Task Force on Lesbian and Gay Men's Concerns. Toy's activism on behalf of gay rights also extended into the political and public policy arena. A willing participant in any number of organizations, causes, and public demonstrations, Toy urged change on all levels of government.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">He was on the committee that drafted an anti-discrimination ordinance (perhaps the first such official proclamation in the United States) for the city of Ann Arbor that was adopted in July 1972. That same year he co-authored a Gay Pride Week proclamation subsequently approved by the city council of Ann Arbor. On the state level, Toy served as a member of the Task Force on the Family and Sexuality of the Civil Rights Committee of the Michigan State House of Representatives.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="545" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Other organizations in which Toy participated included the local chapter of the ACLU, the state board of the Michigan Organization for Human Rights, the Ann Arbor Area Association for Civil Concerns, the Lesbian/Gay Political Caucus of Washtenaw County, and the Huron Valley Chapter of Wellness Network (now the HIV/AIDS Resource Center, or HARC).</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1="2" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The James Toy collection consists of materials created and/or collected over a three decade period, mainly from 1971 to 1994. It is a combination of the personal papers of Toy and the records of the university office (originally named Human Sexuality Office, later Lesbian-Gay Male Programs Office, and now Lesbian-Gay Male-Bisexual Programs Office) in which Toy was employed for twenty-five years.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1="2" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The Toy Papers have been arranged into three series: Lesbian-Gay Male-Bisexual Programs Office, Topical Files, and Correspondence. The Lesbian-Gay Male-Bisexual Programs Office series consists of records generated by Toy (with some records of the lesbian advocate) in his capacity as gay male advocate within the Human Sexuality Office (and successor units) of the University of Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1="2" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">These records relate to the administration of the office, its programs, and its relationship with the larger university community. Of special note are those files pertaining to the effort to revise the U-M Regental Bylaw 14.06 and thus provide protection against discrimination on the basis of sexual orientation, the work of the U-M Task Force on Sexual Orientation, and the drafting of the two policy statements on discrimination and discriminatory harassment (for students, and for faculty and staff).</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1="2" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">The Topical Files series consists mainly of subject files, collected or created by Toy, and relating to his involvement or mentoring of other gay organizations. Organizations represented with significant amounts of material include the Gay Hotline, the Gay Liberation Front, the Gay Community Services, LaGROC, and the Michigan Organization for Human Rights.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="520" ind1="2" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Other portions of this series pertain to Toy's numerous committee and training responsibilities within the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan and on the general topic of the attitude of the various religious denominations to the topic of homosexuality and the inclusion of gays into church life.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="506" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Restricted access in part.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="555" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Finding aid in the library.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="555" ind1="0" ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Finding aid available via World Wide Web at URL: http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead&amp;idno=umich-bhl-9744</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="500" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">Donor: 8504</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="600" ind1="1" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Toy, James W.,</subfield>
    <subfield code="d">1930-</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Ann Arbor Gay Liberation Front.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">AIDS (Disease)</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="651" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Ann Arbor (Mich.)</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Coming out (Sexual orientation)</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Episcopal Church.</subfield>
    <subfield code="b">Diocese of Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Episcopal Church</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Gay college students</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Ann Arbor.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Gay liberation movement</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Gay men</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Gays</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Homosexuality</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Homosexuality</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Ann Arbor.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Homosexuality</subfield>
    <subfield code="x">Religious aspects</subfield>
    <subfield code="x">Episcopal Church.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Lesbians</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Michigan Organization for Human Rights.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="650" ind1=" " ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">Sexual orientation</subfield>
    <subfield code="z">Michigan.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">University of Michigan.</subfield>
    <subfield code="b">Human Sexuality Office.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">University of Michigan.</subfield>
    <subfield code="b">Lesbian-Gay Male Programs Office.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">University of Michigan.</subfield>
    <subfield code="b">Study Committee on the Status of Lesbians and Gay Men.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="610" ind1="2" ind2="0">
    <subfield code="a">University of Michigan.</subfield>
    <subfield code="b">Task Force on Sexual Orientation.</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="852" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="b">Bentley Historical Library,</subfield>
    <subfield code="a">University of Michigan,</subfield>
    <subfield code="e">Ann Arbor, Michigan 48109-2113</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="856" ind1="4" ind2="2">
    <subfield code="3">Finding aid:</subfield>
    <subfield code="u">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead&amp;idno=umich-bhl-9744</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="997" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="a">MARS</subfield>
  </datafield>
  <datafield tag="998" ind1=" " ind2=" ">
    <subfield code="c">TEP</subfield>
  </datafield>
</record>
