<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::micrgunown.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier"> umich-bhl-2008027</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for Michigan Coalition for Responsible Gun Owners records. </titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by Max Eckard </author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
        <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2015"> 2015</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created by Olga Virakhovskaya <date>2015</date></creation>
      <langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date>2015-10-07</date>
        <item>Original encoding from Word 10.0 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
    <classification ref="/repositories/2/classifications/1"/>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <publisher>Michigan Historical Collections <lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>
      <titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/> Michigan Coalition for Responsible Gun Owners records </titleproper>
      <author>Finding aid created by<lb/> Max Eckard, in September 2015. </author>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="recordgrp" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did>
      <origination>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="110" ref="/agents/corporate_entities/937"> Michigan Coalition for Responsible Gun Owners </corpname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="245">Michigan Coalition for Responsible Gun Owners records</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1994/2007"> 1994-2007 </unitdate><physdesc altrender="part">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1.09 GB</extent>
        <physfacet>online</physfacet>
      </physdesc>
      <unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number"> 2008027 Bj 2 </unitid>
      <langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>
      <abstract> Historical documents of the Michigan Coalition for Responsible Gun Owners collected by organization president David K. Felbeck, including board minutes, newspaper articles, web pages, correspondence, images, and other documents. Chiefly Microsoft Word files, also some website files and other formats. </abstract>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
        <extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </repository>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admin">
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
        <p> Donated by David K. Felbeck (Donor No. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">9993</num>) in January 2002. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accruals encodinganalog="584">
        <p> No further additions to the records are expected. </p>
      </accruals>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
        <p>Collection is open for research. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
        <p> Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan. Researchers may make copies of single documents only. Entire .zip files may not be copied</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
        <p>[item], folder, box, Michigan Coalition for Responsible Gun Owners records, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo>
        <p>
          <extptr href="digitalproc" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
        </p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
      <p>Formed in 1996 by only eight concealed pistol advocates in the successful fight to implement "shall-issue" concealed carry in Michigan, the Michigan Coalition for Responsible Gun Owners (MCRGO) is a non-profit, non-partisan organization whose mission is to "promot[e] safe use and ownership of firearms through education, litigation and legislation" (http://mcrgo.org/about-mcrgo/ accessed in September 2015). As of 2015 it has paid full time staff and is Michigan's largest, non-profit, state-based firearms organization.</p>
      <p>In addition to assisting allied groups including Students for Concealed Carry, Michigan Open Carry, and Michigan Gun Owners, the MCRGO is actively involved with firearms-related legislation in Michigan, and were active in the concealed carry reform law of 2000 and the revisions to it that were passed in 2002. They maintain a Political Action Committee registered with the Bureau of Elections of the State of Michigan which has helped many pro-firearm legislators in state-wide elections.</p>
      <p>Board members of MCRGO are elected from the membership, and membership dues support MCRGO activities, including the distribution of information though traditional media including guest editorials in local Michigan newspapers, town-hall meetings interviews on radio and television and participation in community forums and local government meetings. They also issue a quarterly newsletter entitled "On Point," which provides detailed background on MCRGO's current work on efforts such as strengthening preemption laws, eliminating no carry zones, ending the practice of granting special firearms rights to special groups, and promoting firearms recreation including both hunting and sport, as well as interviews with prominent gun rights activists. </p>
      <p>The MCRGO has a charitable arm, the MCRGO Foundation. The Foundation has a 501(C)(3) status, and its mission is to educate the public on the Second Amendment, Michigan's Constitutional Right to Bear Arms, and the safe ownership and usage of firearms. A volunteer board of directors administers the Foundation. Board members are selected for their knowledge, experience, and commitment to fostering the intent and goals of the Foundation mission.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <p>Collection is organized into three series: Organizational Records, Historical Documents and Correspondence, and Talking Points.</p>
    </arrangement>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
      <p>The Michigan Coalition for Responsible Gun Owners (MCRGO) records reflect the views and activities of a prominent non-profit organization in Michigan involved in a controversial area of American politics, the fight between gun control activists and gun rights activists. The records are a rich source of information on gun rights and politics in Michigan, as well as the larger, nation-wide debate over the Second Amendment to the U.S. Constitution.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <p>
        <extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </p>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/9340">Firearms--Law and legislation--Michigan.</subject>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610" ref="/agents/corporate_entities/937">Michigan Coalition for Responsible Gun Owners.</corpname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651" ref="/subjects/1993">Michigan--Politics and government--1951-1960.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651" ref="/subjects/2365">Michigan--Politics and government--1991-2000.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651" ref="/subjects/2366">Michigan--Politics and government--2001-2010.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Contributors: </head>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700" ref="/agents/people/3245">Felbeck, David K.</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655" ref="/subjects/3187">Digital file formats.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Organizational Records</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Organizational Records (1999-2006, 0.1 GB) series contains the MCRGO's bylaws and revisions, open and closed minutes from the Board of Directors, records of MCRGO endorsements for the Michigan Legislature, lists of activists, legislators and MCRGO employees, membership application materials and firearms-related bills passed by the Michigan Legislature.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>MCRGO documents and lists</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001/2007">2001-2007</unitdate><physdesc altrender="whole">
              <physfacet>ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113277" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/10512">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[download item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online</physloc>
            <unittitle>Minutes</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001/2003">2001-2003</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>.ZIP file</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113278" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/10513">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[download item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online</physloc>
            <unittitle>Bills</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1999/2006">1999-2006</unitdate><physdesc altrender="whole">
              <physfacet>ZIP files</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113279" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/10514">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[download item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Historical Documents and Correspondence</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Historical Documents and Correspondence (1995-2006, 1.07 GB) series forms the bulk of the collection, containing correspondence with members, gun clubs, and legislators over bills and statutes such as the concealed carry reform law of 2000 and the revisions to it that were passed in 2002, reference files, strategic plans for the organization, website files, letters to the editor and news articles all related to the MCRGO and their work in the state of Michigan, organized chronologically. Also contained in this series are the copies of the MCRGO's "On Point" newsletter. Issues covered in this series include: the Second Amendment to the U.S. Constitution as well as the State of Michigan's similar constitutional right, hunting and fishing, concealed carry, and safe ownership and usage of firearms.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1995/2006">1995-2006</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>(.ZIP file)</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113280" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/10515">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[download item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Talking Points</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The Talking Points (undated, 0.02 GB) series contains a folder entitled "Firearms, Fantasy and Facts". This folder contains files with point/counterpoint-style talking points on firearms-related issues that arose in the media, especially by proponents of gun control. Issues covered in this series include: gun-related trauma and deaths, especially of children, the nature of the Second Amendment to the U.S. Constitution, road rage, gun shows and gun show loopholes for attaining a firearm, as well as questions about the inherent morality of firearms.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>"Firearms, Fantasy and Fact,"</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate><physdesc>
              <physfacet>(.ZIP file)</physfacet>
            </physdesc>
            <dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/113281" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/10516">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[download item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>MCRGO website</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The MCRGO Website series contains an archived version of the MCRGO website, which promotes safe use and ownership of firearms through education, litigation, and legislation resources, as well as resources for anyone involved in the shooting sports.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unittitle>MCRGO website </unittitle>
            <dao href="2008027-w-1" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/10517">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[view item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
