<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::motoliq.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier"> umich-bhl-2013139</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for General Motors Bankruptcy Collection Web Archives </titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by Max Eckard</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
        <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2016"> 2016</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created by Olga Virakhovskaya <date>2016</date></creation>
      <langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date>2016-01-11</date>
        <item>Original encoding from Word 10.0 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
    <classification ref="/repositories/2/classifications/1"/>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <publisher>Michigan Historical Collections <lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>
      <titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/> General Motors Bankruptcy Collection Web Archives. </titleproper>
      <author>Finding aid created by<lb/> Max Eckard, in January, 2016. </author>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="recordgrp" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did>
      <origination>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="110" ref="/agents/corporate_entities/1819">Motors Liquidation Company</corpname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="245">General Motors Bankruptcy Collection Web Archives</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f"> 2009-ongoing </unitdate><physdesc altrender="part">
        <extent encodinganalog="300" altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">1.03 GB</extent>
        <physfacet>online</physfacet>
      </physdesc>
      <physdesc altrender="part">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">2 archived websites</extent>
        <physfacet>online</physfacet>
      </physdesc>
      <unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number"> 2013139 Aa 3 </unitid>
      <langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>
      <abstract> The Motors Liquidation Company was the company left to settle past liability claims from the government-endorsed General Motors Chapter 11 reorganization which sold the assets of automobile manufacturer General Motors and some of its subsidiaries to NGMCO, Inc. ("New GM"). The collection includes archived websites of the Motors Liquidation Company, containing court documents and a claims register.</abstract>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
        <extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </repository>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admin">
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
        <p> Donated by Motors Liquidation Company (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">11017</num>), in August, 2009. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
        <p>The collection is open without restriction</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
        <p> Copyright has not been transferred to the Regents of the University of Michigan.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
        <p>[item], General Motors Bankruptcy Collection Web Archives, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan.</p>
      </prefercite>
      <processinfo>
        <p>
          <extptr href="digitalproc" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
        </p>
      </processinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
      <p>Motors Liquidation Company, formerly General Motors Corporation, was the company left to settle past liability claims from General Motors Chapter 11 reorganization. </p>
      <p>On June 1, 2009, General Motors Corporation and some of its subsidiaries filed for bankruptcy protection in the United States Bankruptcy Court for the Southern District of New York. General Motors' attorneys preferred to file in the federal courts in New York because of their reputation for expertise in bankruptcy. This was followed swiftly by press conferences by General Motors' Chief Executive Officer, Fritz Henderson, who outlined a plan for NGMCO, Inc. ("New GM") and stressed that he intended for the process to move quickly, and President of the United States Barack Obama, who presented a rescue plan.</p>
      <p>In the bankruptcy case, <title render="italic">In re General Motors Corp.</title>, case number 09-50026 in the Southern District, Manhattan, New York, General Motors was represented by Weil, Gotshal and Manges, a specialist law firm in New York and was declared to be a debtor in possession. The United States Treasury and an ad hoc group of the bondholders of General Motors Corporation were also represented in court. After voiding the leases on seven corporate jets and a corporate aircraft hangar, on June 1, 2009, the court gave interim approval to GM's request to borrow $15 billion as debtor-in-possession financing, the company having only $2 billion cash in hand. The United States Treasury would be the source of that debtor in possession funding.</p>
      <p>Later that year, General Motors' good assets were sold to NCGMO, Inc. ("New GM"), a company that had been formed by the United States government with a 60% stake and others. "Old GM" was renamed Motors Liquidation Company. On July 10, 2009, the purchase of the ongoing operational assets--with the exception of Hummer, Saturn and Saab--and trade name of "old GM" was completed and NGMCO Inc. changed its name to "General Motors Company LLC" after the purchase. </p>
      <p>Motors Liquidation Company exited bankruptcy on March 31, 2011 only to be carved into four trusts; the first to settle the claims of unsecured, the second to handle environmental response for Motors Liquidation Company's remaining assets, a third to handle present and future asbestos-related claims and a fourth for litigation claims.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
      <p>Motors Liquidation Company bankruptcy website is evidence of the automotive industry crisis of 2008-2010, caused in part by the confluence of the global financial turndown of the late-2000s recession, record oil prices, a severe global automotive sales decline due to the global financial crisis of 2008--2009. This collection of archived websites contains court documents and a claims register for the company left to settle past liability claims from General Motors Chapter 11 reorganization, and is arranged in a single series, Archived Websites.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <p>
        <extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </p>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79079577" ref="/agents/corporate_entities/177">General Motors Corporation.</corpname>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/6905">Bankruptcy--Michigan--Detroit.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/6921">Liquidation--Michigan--Detroit.</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/6911">Corporations--Michigan--Detroit.</subject>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651" ref="/subjects/2400">Michigan.</geogname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79045539" ref="/subjects/929">Detroit (Mich.)</geogname>
        <subject source="local" encodinganalog="690" ref="/subjects/3523">Commerce and industry.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655" ref="/subjects/3332">Web sites.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Archived Websites</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <physloc>Online </physloc>
            <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2009">2009</unitdate><dao href="http://hdl.handle.net/2027.42/116381" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/10570">
              <daodesc>
                <p>[download item]</p>
              </daodesc>
            </dao>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>2010-ongoing</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <physloc>Online </physloc>
              <unittitle>Motors Liquidation Company website </unittitle>
              <dao href="https://wayback.archive-it.org/org-934/*/http://www.motorsliquidationdocket.com" show="new" actuate="onRequest" ref="/repositories/2/digital_objects/10571">
                <daodesc>
                  <p>[view item]</p>
                </daodesc>
              </dao>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
