<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::plecharyan.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier"> umich-bhl-2016018</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for Ryan C. Plecha papers </titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by Olga Virakhovskaya </author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
        <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2016"> 2016</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created by Olga Virakhovskaya <date>2016</date></creation>
      <langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date>2016-02-11</date>
        <item>Original encoding from Word 10.0 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
    <classification ref="/repositories/2/classifications/1"/>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <publisher>Michigan Historical Collections <lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>
      <titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/> Ryan C. Plecha papers </titleproper>
      <author>Finding aid created by<lb/> Olga Virakhovskaya, in February 2016 </author>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did>
      <origination>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100" ref="/agents/people/4908"> Plecha, Ryan C. </persname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="245">Ryan C. Plecha papers</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="2013/2014"> 2013-2014 </unitdate><physdesc altrender="whole">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.2 linear feet</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number"> 2016018 Aa 2 </unitid>
      <langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>
      <abstract> Documentation and photographs related to the Detroit Retired City Employees Association and the Detroit's Chapter 9 bankruptcy. </abstract>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
        <extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </repository>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admin">
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
        <p> Donated by Ryan C. Plecha (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">11438</num>) in February 2016. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accruals encodinganalog="584">
        <p>Periodic additions to the records expected.</p>
      </accruals>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
        <p>The collection is open for research. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
        <p> Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan. </p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
        <p>[item], folder, box, Ryan C. Plecha papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p>
      </prefercite>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
      <p> Ryan C. Plecha is a Partner and debt relief attorney at Lippitt O'Keefe Gornbein law firm in Birmingham, Mich. Plecha focuses his practice on civil litigation, complex commercial litigation, estate planning and bankruptcy. </p>
      <p> Plecha graduated cum laude with a Bachelor of Arts from Kalamazoo College and earned his Law Degree from Western Michigan University Thomas M. Cooley Law School. While working on his law degree, Plecha received several prestigious honors, including the Sol Siegal Award and the Shane Joseph Memorial Scholarship. Prior to joining Lippitt O'Keefe Gornbein in 2011, he served as a judicial intern to the Honorable Gerald E. Rosen, Chief Judge, U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan. In 2008, Plecha established Plecha Legal, a general practice firm engaged in cases concerning civil litigation, family law, estate planning, and corporate formations. Between 2009 and 2011 Plecha worked for Hyman Lippitt, PC as a Contract Attorney and an Associate Attorney. During this time he also served as a research and writing clerk on the Michigan Law Revision Commission. </p>
      <p> Plecha's notable successes include providing representation of a Michigan corporation in a multimillion dollar federal antitrust class action suit; representation of a big three automotive company in supplier disputes; representation of two hedge funds in a class action shareholder oppression case; represented Ford Motor Company in various matters; and participated in prosecution of the Fair Labor Standards Act (FLSA) class action on behalf of employees (prison guards) of Michigan Department of Corrections. Plecha was counsel to two Detroit Retiree Associations (the Retired Detroit Police and Fire Fighters Association (RDPFFA), and the Detroit Retired City Employees Association (DRCEA)) in the historic City of Detroit Chapter 9 bankruptcy. The RDPFFA, whose 6,500 members at the time included more than 80 percent of police and fire pensioners, was a Lippitt O'Keefe Gornbein client, and the DRCEA specifically retained the firm for the bankruptcy. The police-fire association reached an agreement to support Detroit's plan of adjustment out of mediation in April 2014 -- one that avoided benefit cuts but reduced cost-of-living increases for pensioners going forward. Other employees and later the boards of Detroit's two employee pension funds later got on board with the city's plan as well. </p>
      <p> Plecha is a member of the Oakland County Bar Association, the American Bankruptcy Institute, the American Bar Association, the Federal Bar Association and The Oakland County Bar Association American Inn of Court. In 2013 Plecha was appointed to the executive council of the State Bar of Michigan's Young Lawyers Section. He is admitted to practice law in the state of Michigan as well as before the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan and the United States Court of Appeals for the 6th Circuit. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
      <p> DRCEA and RDPFFA communications and press releases; U.S. Bankruptcy Court Eastern District of Michigan notices; statements by Shirley V. Lightsey, President of the DRCEA, and Don Taylor, President of RDPFFA; photographs.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <p>
        <extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </p>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79045539" ref="/subjects/929">Detroit (Mich.)</geogname>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610" ref="/agents/corporate_entities/3465">Detroit Retired City Employees Association.</corpname>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/9781">Municipal bankruptcy--Michigan--Detroit.</subject>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600" ref="/agents/people/4908">Plecha, Ryan C.</persname>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610" ref="/agents/corporate_entities/831">Retired Detroit Police and Fire Fighters Association.</corpname>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" ref="/subjects/9782">Retirees--Michigan--Detroit.</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre Terms:</head>
        <genreform source="aat" encodinganalog="655" ref="/subjects/3135">Photographs.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Ryan C. Plecha papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [44253619694492672223291]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Detroit Retired City Employees Association </unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [44253619694492672223291]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Retired Detroit Police and Fire Fighters Association</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box [44253619694492672223291]">1</container>
            <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
