<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core" scriptencoding="iso15924" countryencoding="iso3166-1">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::briggsfamwash.xml//EN" encodinganalog="Identifier"> umich-bhl-2016017</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="Title">Finding Aid for Briggs family (Washtenaw County, Mich.) papers </titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="Creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by Benjamin Bond </author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="Publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
        <date encodinganalog="Date" normal="2016"> 2016</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created by Olga Virakhovskaya <date>2016</date></creation>
      <langusage encodinganalog="Language">The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules>Finding aid prepared using Describing Archives: A Content Standard (DACS)</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date>2016-03-11</date>
        <item>Original encoding from Word 10.0 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <publisher><lb/>Bentley Historical Library<lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>
      <titleproper>Finding aid for<lb/> Briggs family (Washtenaw County, Mich.) papers </titleproper>
      <author>Finding aid created by<lb/> Benjamin Bond, in February, 2016 </author>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="recordgrp" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did>
      <origination>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100"> Briggs family </persname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="245"> Briggs family (Washtenaw County, Mich.) papers <unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f"> 1862-1865, after 1876 and undated </unitdate> <unitdate type="bulk" encodinganalog="245$g" normal="1862/1864">1862-1864</unitdate> </unittitle>
      <physdesc altrender="whole">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.4 linear feet</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <unitid encodinganalog="852$h" repositorycode="miu-h" countrycode="us" type="call number"> 2016017 Aa 2 </unitid>
      <langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language> </langmaterial>
      <abstract> Residents of Pittsfield Township, Washtenaw County, Mich., John Briggs and his sons George and Clark served in the Union army during the American Civil War. John and George volunteered in the Michigan 6th Cavalry while Clark served in the 20th Infantry. The collection consists of approximately 100 letters written by the Briggs between 1862 and 1864 addressed to Mary Briggs, the wife of John and mother of George and Clark. Also, photocopies of George Briggs' military papers and information about the Briggs family.</abstract>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
        <extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </repository>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admin">
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
        <p> Donated by Darwyn H. Briggs (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">11436</num>) in February, 2016. </p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accruals encodinganalog="584">
        <p> No further additions to the records are expected. </p>
      </accruals>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
        <p>The collection is open for research without restrictions. </p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
        <p> Copyright is held by the Regents of the University of Michigan.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
        <p>[item], folder, box, Briggs family (Washtenaw County, Mich.) papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p>
      </prefercite>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
      <p>John Briggs and two of his sons, George and Clark, left their home of Pittsfield Township, Michigan in 1862 to volunteer for service in the Union Army during the American Civil War. John and George served in the Michigan 6th Cavalry, company F while Clark served in the Michigan 20th Infantry. </p>
      <p>John's wife, Mary, and their four younger children remained home on the farm of Van Rensselaer Tyler, Mary's father and early settler of Washtenaw County, Mich. </p>
      <p>The Michigan 6th Cavalry saw action at the Battle of Hanover on July 30th, 1863. At this time they also received their new commander, George Armstrong Custer. On July 2nd it engaged Wade Thompson's cavalry in the Battle of Hunterstown, finding success under the new leadership. The 6th then participated in the famous cavalry fight at Gettysburg on July 3rd, in which it supported Pennington's battery. George and John were wounded during the Confederate retreat the following day and George spent time in military hospitals in Washington D.C. and Annapolis. John was taken as a prisoner to Richmond, VA. He spent the next year and a half a prisoner of war, moving from prisons to a hospital and back again. He was finally paroled on December 6th, 1864, but died in an Annapolis hospital less than a month later due to "typhoid pneumonia". </p>
      <p>George recovered from his wounds and went on to participate in every battle the 6th was a part of, including Buckland Mills, The Wilderness, Yellow Tavern, Hawes Shop, Winchester, Shepardstown, and Tom's Brook. He was killed on October 23rd, 1864 in Virginia at Cedar Creek, Middleton, or Bills Mill; the records are unclear and contradictory. It is recorded in an officer's report that George was killed by a civilian as he approached a farmhouse. </p>
      <p>There is much less information regarding the military career of Clark Briggs. However, it is known that he was killed in action at the Battle of Spotsylvania Courthouse, between May 8th and 21st, 1864.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
      <p>Approximately 100 letters written by soldiers John, George, and Clark Briggs between 1862 and 1865, constitute the bulk of the collection. The majority are addressed to Mary Briggs, the rest to Van Rensselaer Tyler. Most of the letters are matched with the envelope in which they were originally housed, although a number of letters and envelopes remain unmatched. Other materials include a chronological list and a brief summary of Briggs letters, a list of Briggs family members born between 1794 and 1876, photocopies of George Briggs military papers, and modern-day background biographical information about the Briggs. </p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <p>
        <extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </p>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <famname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Briggs family.</famname>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Briggs, Clark C.</persname>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Briggs, George E.</persname>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Briggs, John L.</persname>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Soldiers--Michigan--Pittsfield (Township)</subject>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Soldiers--Michigan--Washtenaw County.</subject>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">United States. Army. Michigan 6th Cavalry. Company F.</corpname>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">United States. Army. Michigan 20th Infantry.</corpname>
        <geogname source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Briggs family papers</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The bulk of the collection is represented by approximately 100 letters written by soldiers John, George, and Clark Briggs between 1862 and 1864. The majority of letters is addressed to Mary Briggs, the rest to Van Rensselaer Tyler. Most of the letters are matched with the envelope in which they were originally housed, although a number of letters and envelopes remain unmatched. A chronological list and a brief summary of letters are also included. Collection also includes modern-day biographical essays, photocopies of George Briggs military papers, and modern-day property maps.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
            <unittitle>Background biographical information</unittitle>
          </did>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
            <unittitle>George Briggs military papers </unittitle>
          </did>
          <odd>
            <p>(photocopies)</p>
          </odd>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Letters</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>Summary and chronology</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>
                <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1862">1862</unitdate>
              </unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>
                <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1863">1863</unitdate>
              </unittitle>
              <physdesc altrender="whole">
                <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">2 folders</extent>
              </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>
                <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1864">1864</unitdate>
              </unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>
                <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1865">1865</unitdate>
              </unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>
                <unitdate type="inclusive">Undated</unitdate>
              </unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
